Imagine a student from a remote part of J&K and Ladakh, full of hope, applying for a scholarship
that would change their lives.
Instead of focusing on the studies, they are caught in a frustrating cycle, printing documents,
traveling to verification centers and waiting for approvals that seem to take forever.
The process is slow, confusing and full of paperwork, often leading to delays that leave
students in a limbo.
But it's not just the students facing the challenges.
On the other side, the FC center is overwhelmed with the task of manually verifying thousands
of documents from the applicants.
Imagine an alternative, a system where students can apply for their scholarships from the
home.
The workflow documents digitally and track their application status in real time.
No paperwork, no long wait times.
The SHE Bureau, too benefit from the automated verification and streamlined workflows enabling
them to review applications faster and with greater accuracy.
This is exactly what we, Team CODENITI, aim to achieve with our paperless scholarship
disbursement system for the Prime Minister's special scholarships scheme.
I'm Jheel Jain and along with my team we have built a system that eliminates the need
for manual verification by leveraging technologies like optical character recognition and DigiLocker for
secure document authentication.
Students can upload the documents directly while the SHE Bureau can automate verification
and focus on critical cases by reducing manual steps via ensuring faster, more transparent
and reliable scholarship disbursement.